Guide to the Rave collection, circa 1991-1998.
Rave collection,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Rave collection, circa 1991-1998.
8068
5.2 cubic feet (approximately 8100 items).
Flyers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Batch one consists of San Francisco Bay area rave cards and flyers. 118 items consisting of single sheets, variously folded leaflets, and a few pamphlets, almost all of them printed on paper or card stocks, two or there on acetate and ranging in size from 24mo to 4to, with the majority being 8vo. Some references include, Melville, Whitman, Sendak, Lewis Carroll, Dr. Seuss, Margaret Meade and rock posters of the 1960s.
Rave flyers became one of the most potent symbols of youth culture in the 1990s. Their bright colors signifying a return to psychedelia, their computer-generated design a clue to future technology fetishes, their dense text an invitation to a subculture with its own deities and language. As the popularity of raves grew, it became essential to create flashy, eye-catching flyers to outdo all the other flyers. Flyers grew in both size and complexity. Imported from Chicago in the late 1980s, the English Rave scene paired the country's youth counter culture with house music and Ecstasy and led to a club scene community that could generate parties with thousands of participants, spilling over from London warehouses to countryside fields. English DJs developed their own sound, drawing upon American Hip Hop imports and accessible at-home technologies. The music found its way to radio through pirate stations, and a few bands like Prodigy and N-Joi were able to crossover to FM pop stations.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Batch one consists of San Francisco Bay area rave cards and flyers. 118 items consisting of single sheets, variously folded leaflets, and a few pamphlets, almost all of them printed on paper or card stocks, two or there on acetate and ranging in size from 24mo to 4to, with the majority being 8vo. Some references include, Melville, Whitman, Sendak, Lewis Carroll, Dr. Seuss, Margaret Meade and rock posters of the 1960s.
Batch two consists of more than 500 rave flyers and stickers, primarily from San Francisco, together with five related newsletters and pamphlets. They feature many of the most popular artists and DJs of the time, such as Moby, Deee-Lite, Prodigy, Todd Terry, Juan Atkins, Peter Tong, Sasha, Roger Sanchez, Derrick Carter, Mark Farina, and many others. Also included are a dozen or more flyers from show promoters, lifestyle retailers (neo-head shops and fashion boutiques), spiritual organizations, and related art exhibitions. The flyers reflect the growing sophistication of the rave scene during the period and its various subcategories such as house, trance, techno, drum and bass, hardcore and others. Performers and DJs represented include Moby, Shamen, Deee-Lite, Rozalla, Prodigy, Daft Punk, The Crystal Method, Fluke, Tony Largo, Markie-Mark, Neon Leon, DJ Ghost, Todd Terry, Peter Avila, Danny Morales, Derrick Carter, Mark Farina, Sasha (Welsh), "Little Louie" Vega, DJ Dimitri, Peter Tong, Juan Atkins, DJ Sanchez, DJ Phil Smart, Graeme Park, DJ Destructo, Yagi, and DJ Dag. The rave-related periodicals in the collection include Ameba Message, number 2 (December 23, 1992), and Rhythmos, number 1 (August 1992). Pamphlets include E info: practical information about Ecstasy (no date); The Imaginal Rave (July 1992), signed Cinnamon Twist; and Tribal Donut #1 (1993), a collection of reprints and excerpts from various New Age and rave books and articles.
Batch three is a collection of 1500 English Rave flyers, collected from approximately 1990 to 1996, advertising parties throughout England featuring such acts as The Prodigy, Justin Berkman, and Adam Realtime.
Batch four consists of a decade of rave flyers from England and is a collection of 6000 English Rave flyers, collected from approximately 1990 to 2000 by an early participant in the London rave scene. Most flyers are for events in England, though Ireland, Scotland, the Netherlands, and Australia are also represented.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Atkins, Juan.; Avila, Peter.; Carter, Derrick L.; Cinnamon Twist.; DJ Dag.; DJ Destructo.; DJ Dimitri.; DJ Ghost.; DJ Sanchez.; Farina, Mark.; Largo, Tony.; Little Louie.; Moby.; Morales, Danny.; Neon Leon.; Park, Graeme.; Rozalla.; Sanchez, Roger, 1967-; Smart, Phil.; Terry, Todd.; Tong, Peter.; Wahlberg, Mark, 1971-; Welsh, Sasha.; Yagi.; Crystal Method (Musical group); Daft Punk (Musical group); Deee-Lite (Musical group); Fluke (Musical group); Prodigy (Musical group: Great Britain); Shamen (Musical group)
Subjects:
Music, publicity.; Printed ephemera.; Rave culture.; Rave culture -- California -- San Francisco.; Rave culture -- Great Britain.; House music.; Techno music.; Trance music.; Hardcore (Music).; New Age movement.
Form and Genre Terms:
Fliers (printed matter); Stickers.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. First Batch, California
Box 8
Series II. Second Batch, California
Box 8
Series III. Third Batch, England
Boxes 6-7
Series IV. Fourth Batch, England
Boxes 1-5
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. First Batch, California, 118 items (Box 8, Folder 1-8)
  Mostly San Francisco
- Series II. Second Batch, California, apx. 500 items (Box 8, Folder 9-16)
  The rave-related periodicals in the collection include Ameba Message, number 2 (December 23, 1992), and Rhythmos, number 1 (August 1992). Pamphlets include E info: practical information about Ecstasy (no date); The Imaginal Rave (July 1992), signed Cinnamon Twist; and Tribal Donut #1 (1993), a collection of reprints and excerpts from various New Age and rave books and articles.
- Series III. Third Batch, England, 1992-1994; apx. 1500 items
  - Rave culture publications (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes Fantazia Fanzine (Issue 1), Ravescene (Nos. 22 and 29), and Eazy (No. 2).
  - Rave culture associated advertising (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Includes ads for albums, club memberships, clothing, and drugs.
  - Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Flyers square, ca. 4.5" x 4.5" to 8.5" x 8.5" (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Flyers long, largest ca. 6" x 12" (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Flyers ca. 9" x 12" (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Flyers ca. 9" x 12" (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Flyers ca. 9" x 12" (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Flyers ca. 4" x 5" (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Flyers ca. 4" x 5" (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Flyers ca. 4" x 5" (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Flyers ca. 4" x 5" (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Flyers ca. 4" x 5" (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Flyers ca. 4.25" x 5.5" (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Flyers ca. 4.25" x 5.5" (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Flyers ca. 4.25" x 5.5" (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Flyers ca. 4.25" x 5.5" (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Flyers ca. 4.25" x 5.5" (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Flyers ca. 4.25" x 5.5" (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Flyers ca. 4.25" x 5.5" (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Flyers ca. 4.25" x 5.5" (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Flyers, oddly shaped (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Flyers ca. 12" x 18" (Box 7)
- Series IV. Fourth Batch, England, apx. 6000 items
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12" (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12" (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12" (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Event Flyers ca. 9" x 12" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Flyers, oddly shaped, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Flyers, oddly shaped, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Flyers, oddly shaped, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Flyers, oddly shaped, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Flyers, oddly shaped, 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Flyers, oddly shaped (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rave culture associated advertising, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rave culture associated advertising, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rave culture associated advertising, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rave culture associated advertising, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Rave culture associated advertising, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Rave culture associated advertising, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Rave culture associated advertising, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rave culture associated advertising, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rave culture associated advertising (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1990 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1994 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1997 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1997 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 1999 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25", 2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Event Flyers ca. 5.75" x 8.25" (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Event Quarter cards (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Event flyers - small (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Event flyers - small (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Event flyers - small (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Flyers - oversized, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Flyers - oversized, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Flyers - oversized, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Flyers - oversized, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Flyers - oversized, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Flyers - oversized, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Flyers - oversized, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Flyers - oversized, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Flyers - oversized, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Flyers - oversized, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Flyers - oversized, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Flyers - oversized (Box 5, Folder 12)